Donald J. Winslow Family Papers MS146
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Donald J. Winslow Family Papers
1895 -- 2010
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Winslow, Donald J.
MS146
2.0 Linear Feet
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series; Guy Winslow papers; Donald J. Winslow's writing and research; Donald J. Winslow's personal and family materials.
Biographical / Historical
Donald J. Winslow was born to Guy Monroe and Clara Austin Winslow on December 21, 1911. Winslow was born in Newton and attended Tufts University from 1930-1934, where he was a member of the Delta Upsilon fraternity and the editor of the Tufts Weekly during his senior year.
Winslow graduated in 1934 with a bachelor's degree in English. Because there were few suitable jobs during the Depression, Tufts offered graduates who could not find a job the possibility to complete a master's free of charge. Donald Winslow benefited from this offer and eventually graduated with a master's in English in 1935. He then earned his doctorate in English at Boston University in 1942 and joined its faculty shortly thereafter. Except for his years of military service during World War II, Winslow taught at Boston University for 41 years. He chaired its English Department from 1952-62 and retired in 1977.
During his retirement, Winslow worked as a bibliographer for the journal Biography, taught courses on biography, and continued to publish on Thomas Hardy. When creating the online auto-biographical exhibit for DCA in 2008, he was still working as an historian and archivist for the College Archives at Lasell College in Auburndale, Massachusetts. Winslow married Lois Ella Nelson in 1941 and had two children, Paul Nelson and the late Sanford Austin. Louis and Donald were divorced in 1963. Later on, Donald Winslow married Charlotte Holt Lindgren, a professor of English at Emerson College. Winslow's father, Guy Winslow, was also a Tufts graduate (A.B. 1895, Ph.D. 1898) who served as a Trustee of Tufts for over 30 years.
Donald J. Winslow died July 10, 2010 at his home in Newton, Massachusetts. He is survived by his wife, Charlotte Lindgren Winslow, and his son Paul Nelson.
Custodial History
Some material in this collection is from the vertical files created by Russell Miller and has no provenance or original order. The remaining material was donated, without original order, to Tufts by Donald Winslow in summer 2007.
Donald Winslow has donated portions of his personal papers (including research notes, family documents, historic photographs, and rare books) to several archives and individuals over the years. This collection, donated to DCA in fall of 2007, consists of individual items that had a clear Tufts connection. For other material, researchers should contact the archives at Lasall College and the city archives of Turner, Maine.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes Donald Winslow's personal material relating to Tufts University, as well as information about the Winslow and Russell families and their connections to Tufts. Includes photographs and biographical information, Tufts reunion materials, Commencement programs, and yearbooks, articles by Donald Winslow and other Winslow family members, two film reels from 1926/27 that include footage of Tufts' President Cousens visiting the family in Turner, Maine; and four sketches by Donald Winslow written in the fall of 2007 which document his earliest memories of Tufts. Three Tufts lapel pins are also included in the collection. Also included are a journal and photograph album by Guy Winslow, father of Donald J. Winslow.
Alumni collections; University history; Tufts University -- History; Tufts University
- Guy M. Winslow papers, 1895 -- 1957; 1934 -- 1982; MS146.001; 1.0 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains personal and research materials related to Guy M. Winslow (A1898). Materials include correspondence, photographs, clippings, and articles, along with a journal and a small photo album from approximately 1895. Also included is a research report title, "The Chrondrocranium in the ichthyopsida", a Delta Upsilon lapel pin, and a household microscope.
  Arrangement
  This series is not arranged.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Winslow, Guy M., 1898 -- 1957; MS146.001.001.00001 (Box MS146 Shared 1)
    Material in this file was pulled from Russell Miller's vertical files in January 2009. This folder includes photographs of Guy Winslow.
  - Guy Winslow A1898 M1904 journal, 1895 -- 1902; MS146.001.001.00002 (Box MS146 Shared 1)
    Guy Winslow graduated from the college of Arts & Sciences in 1885, and received a Masters degree in 1898. Photocopies journals date from March 1895 through September 1902.
  - Guy Winslow photo album, 1895; MS146.001.001.00003 (Box MS146 Shared 1)
    The self-made photo album includes photographs of faculty and students, many of which are identified.
  - Tufts College Studies No. 5: The Chrondrocranium in the ichthyopsida, 1898; MS146.001.001.00004; Winslow, Guy M. (Box MS146 Shared 1)
    This folder contains the results of an investigation by Guy Monroe Winslow, published by the Charles Hyde Olmstead Fund.
  - Delta Upsilon pin, 1898; MS146.001.003.00001 (Box MS146 Shared 2)
    This is a jeweled Delta Upsilon lapel pin that belonged to Guy Winslow.
  - Guy Winslow's household microscope, 1900; MS146.001.003.00005 (Box MS146 Shared 2)
    This is a Universal Household Microscope, produced by James W. Queen in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. The viewing crystal on this microscope is cracked and in need of replacement.
- Donald J. Winslow personal and family materials, 1918 -- 2010; 1934 -- 1982; MS146.002; 1.5 Linear Feet
  This series contains Donald Winslow's personal material relating to Tufts University. It includes copies of the Tufts Jumbo, Delta Upsilon materials, Ivy books, and two film reels of the Winslow family in Turner, Maine.
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - [Biographical materials] Winslow, Donald J., 1918 -- 2001; MS146.002.001.00005 (Box MS146 Shared 1)
    Material in this file was pulled from Russell Miller's vertical files: no accession number.
  - Books and documents given to libraries, museums, etc. [1 of 2], 1980 -- 2001; MS146.002.001.00006; Winslow, Donald J. (Box MS146 Shared 1)
  - Books and documents given to libraries, museums, etc. [2 of 2], 1980 -- 2001; MS146.002.001.00007; Winslow, Donald J. (Box MS146 Shared 1)
  - Class of 1934 25th reunion materials, 1959; MS146.002.001.00008 (Box MS146 Shared 1)
  - Correspondence, mostly Tufts-related, 1972 -- 2001; MS146.002.001.00009 (Box MS146 Shared 1)
  - Delta Upsilon materials, Oracle and membership directory, 1930 -- 1997; MS146.002.001.00010 (Box MS146 Shared 1)
    This folder contains a photograph from 1930, a Delta Upsilon membership directory from 1997, and copies or fragments from Delta Upsilon's newsletter, The Oracle, from 1932 and 1981.
  - Family photographs, 1930 -- 2008; MS146.002.001.00011 (Box MS146 Shared 1)
    This folder contains photographs of Donald J. Winslow and members of the Winslow family. Photographs of Guy Winslow are available in MS146.001.001.00001. This folder also contains more recent photograph of Guy Winslow's great grandson standing in front of Winslow's models on display at the American Museum of Natural History.
  - Ivy books, 1930 -- 1935; MS146.002.001.00012 (Box MS146 Shared 1)
  - Judson, Dr. Walter Emery materials, 1945 -- 1975; MS146.002.001.00013 (Box MS146 Shared 1)
    This folder contains materials collected by Donald Winslow, related to his friend Dr. Walter Emery Judson (A38).
  - Jumbo Book, 1934; MS146.002.002.00001 (Box 2)
    This is Donald J. Winslow's copy of the 1934 Jumbo. It contains notes and jottings, probably written by Winslow.
  - Jumbo Book, 1935; MS146.002.002.00002 (Box 2)
    This is Anne Hey's copy of the 1935 Jumbo Book. It contains notes on classmates, including updates on names, professions and address information. It also contains notes and signatures from select classmates, presumably from the time of graduation.
  - Jumbo Book, 1937; MS146.002.002.00003 (Box 2)
    This is Donald Winslow's sister, Priscilla Winslow's copy of the 1937 Jumbo Book. It contains notes on classmates, mainly indicated if individuals were deceased.
  - The Life and Lineage of Hilmer H. and Grace W. Lingren, 2009; MS146.002.002.00004; Winslow, Charlotte Lindgren (Box 2)
    This is a book of Lindgren family history written by Donald Winslow's wife, Charlotte Lindgren Winslow. Chapter VII, "A Late Marriage" details the lives of both Donald and Charlotte and tells of their meeting and marriage.
  - Map: Tufts College in Medford and Boston, 1956; MS146.002.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Memorial service: remarks and program, 2010; MS146.002.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Odds and Ends: Personal Papers of Donald J. Winslow, 1936 -- 2001; MS146.002.002.00007 (Box 2)
    This folder contains Donald J. Winslow's resume, important correspondence, newspaper clippings, and select essays by Winslow.
  - Reunion and commencement materials, 1937 -- 1997; MS146.002.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - Russell family materials, 1989 -- 2006; MS146.002.002.00009 (Box 2)
  - Delta Upsilon frat pin, 1934; MS146.002.003.00002 (Box MS146 Shared 2)
    This is a Delta Upsilon lapel pin that belonged to Donald Winslow.
  - Tufts Weekly editor pin, 1934; MS146.002.003.00003 (Box MS146 Shared 2)
    This is a Tufts Weekly lapel pin that belonged to Donald Winslow.
  - Class of 1934 50th reunion pin, 1984; MS146.002.003.00004 (Box MS146 Shared 2)
    This is a class of 1934 50th reunion lapel pin that belonged to Donald Winslow.
  - [Film Reel (2 of 2)], 1926 -- 1927; MS146.002.003.00006 (Box MS146 Shared 2)
    Footage of the Winslow family at their summer home in Turner, ME, as well as shots of President Cousens.
  - [Film Reel (1 of 2)], 1926 -- 1927; MS146.002.003.00007 (Box MS146 Shared 2)
- Donald J. Winslow writings, 1922 -- 2008; 1934 -- 1982; MS146.003; 0.5 Linear Feet
  This series contains pieces of fiction and non-fiction written by Donald Winslow.
  - Anthony, written at age 13, 1924; MS146.003.004.00001; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)
  - A Young Lad of Ticonderoga, written at age 14, 1925; MS146.003.004.00002; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)
    This short novel was given as a birthday gift from Donald Winslow to his mother.
  - Family Affairs newsletter, 1922 -- 1925; MS146.003.004.00003; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)
    This folder contains five issues of Donald Winslow's family subscription newsletter.
  - The Tuftonian, 1932 -- 1934; MS146.003.004.00004; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)
    This issue of the Tuftonian contains Donald Winslow's fiction piece, "Night."
  - Education for Peace, commencement address, 1934; MS146.003.004.00005; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)
    This folder contains a commencement speech written by Donald Winslow, delivered at the 1934 ceremony.
  - Thomas Hardy: His British and American Critics, abstract of a dissertation, 1942; MS146.003.004.00006; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)
    This is an abstract of Donald Winslow's dissertation for his PhD in Philosophy from Boston University.
  - The Thomas Hardy Year Book, 1970; MS146.003.004.00007; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)
    This publication contains an essay by Donald Winslow, "A Call on Thomas Hardy's Sister."
  - Life-Writing: A glossary of terms in biography, autobiography and related forms (1st edition), 1980; MS146.003.004.00008; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)
  - Biography, vol. 3 no. 4, 1980; MS146.003.004.00009; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)
    This publication contains an essay written by Donald Winslow and K. A. Bennett, "Current Bibliography on Life-Writing."
  - The Thomas Hardy Year Book, 1981; MS146.003.004.00010; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)
    This publication contains an essay written by Donald Winslow, "Images of Emma Hardy."
  - Thomas Hardy's Sister Kate, 1982; MS146.003.004.00011; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)
  - Life-Writing: A glossary of terms in biography, autobiography and related forms (2nd edition), 1995; MS146.003.004.00012; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)
  - Historic Auburndale, 1996; MS146.003.004.00013; Winslow, Donald J.; Winslow, Charlotte Lindgren (Box 4)
    This publication contains an essay written by Donald J. Winslow and Charlotte Lindgren Winslow, "Auburndale Past."
  - Lasell: A visual history, 2001; MS146.003.004.00014; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)
  - Youthful verse and Youthful Prose, 1934 -- 2004; MS146.003.004.00015; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)
    This book contains poetry, essays, and articles written by Donald J. Winslow.
  - Thoughts on Religion: Leonard Woolf letters in 1967 / Leonard Woolf from SOWING (vol. 1 autobiography) / D.J.W. God and Other Matters, 1960 -- 2004; MS146.003.004.00016; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)
    This booklet contains writings and essays on god and religion collected and written by Donald Winslow. A message on the cover states, "The ultimate blessing is the return to non-being."
  - Short essays, 2008; MS146.003.004.00017; Winslow, Donald J. (Box 4)